<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Federico's Blog - misc</title><link href="https://federicov.github.io/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://federicov.github.io/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://federicov.github.io/</id><updated>2014-09-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><subtitle>Machine Learning, Causal Inference, and whatever else I find interesting</subtitle><entry><title>EuroSciPy 2014 Thoughts</title><link href="https://federicov.github.io/EuroSciPy2014.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2014-09-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2014-09-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Federico Vaggi</name></author><id>tag:federicov.github.io,2014-09-05:/EuroSciPy2014.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just got back from Cambridge, where last week I attended &lt;a href="https://www.euroscipy.org/"&gt;EuroSciPy&lt;/a&gt;.  It was by far one of the best conferences I've ever attended and, from my point of view, the organizers basically did everything right.  I wanted to draw some sort of best practices, in the hope that other …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just got back from Cambridge, where last week I attended &lt;a href="https://www.euroscipy.org/"&gt;EuroSciPy&lt;/a&gt;.  It was by far one of the best conferences I've ever attended and, from my point of view, the organizers basically did everything right.  I wanted to draw some sort of best practices, in the hope that other organizers try to imitate what works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Best Conference Practices:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The organizers didn't attempt to pack too many talks every day.&lt;/strong&gt;  Most days, talks finished around 5:30 PM, leaving lots of time for people to hang out and get to know each other.  Conferences that last until 7PM, with evening sessions after dinner result in massive burnout by the end of the conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The conference was very cheap.&lt;/strong&gt;  Due to generosity of the sponsors and the excellent organization, the academic price for the full registration (including tutorials) was 100 pounds for a 4 day conference.  Cambridge was also an excellent location - flying to Stanstead is easy, and the various colleges around town offered cheap accomodation during the off-school period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A very good mix of talks&lt;/strong&gt;.  There was a lot of spotlight for packages used by almost everyone in the scientific community (iPython, scikit-learn, etc) as well as some great talks on some incredibly impressive packages that I'd never heard about before (more on that later).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Everyone was so damn nice&lt;/strong&gt;.  Seriously - even though the community was quite small, as a relative outsider, it didn't feel cliqueish at all, and at the sprints and the social events everyone was very welcoming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few of the packages that caught my eye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New Packages:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/SciTools/biggus/"&gt;Biguss&lt;/a&gt;.  This is a generalization of numpy to handle data which is too big to fit into memory using delayed evaluation.  It's very similar in spirit to Blaze by Continuum, but it's less ambitious and more mature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The optimization tools, and the HPC tools presented by Mike McKerns (https://github.com/uqfoundation).  Mystic looks very interesting (although the documentation is still a bit incomplete) but Dill (a better pickle that handles lots of objects that pickle cannot) and Pathos (a better multiprocessing) I will definitely incorporate into my workflow.  Mike did an excellent work of building tools that work very well together, but are worth using individually, which is a very difficult task that requires a lot of thought about API design and interoperability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/firedrakeproject/firedrake"&gt;Firedrake&lt;/a&gt;.  This is an incredible tool for largescale PDE systems.  The talk by Florian Rathgeber showing off the Firedrake architecture, and how the tool was built on several layers to allow people from different backgrounds to contribute was great.  One issue with the technology that was presented is the team made a lot of effort into separating all the various layers, but they are interlocking enough that it's difficult to use them individually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://julialang.org/"&gt;Julia&lt;/a&gt;.  The keynote by Steven Johnson was very impressive, and some of the things he implemented in there using metaprogramming to achieve greater than Fortran speed by inlining large polynomials seemed almost like black magic.  One of the biggest barriers that new languages face is the lack of a stable ecosystem, but &lt;a href="https://github.com/stevengj/PyCall.jl"&gt;PyCall&lt;/a&gt; (also by Steven Johnson) makes calling Python packages from Julia a breeze - and it does so without message passing across a Python interpreter (like RPy2 or matlab-bridge do), but through some really clever c-api hacks.  I blogged about this earlier (http://federicov.github.io/Blog/Julia-and-Scientific-Python.html):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://pythonhosted.org/Sumatra/"&gt;Sumatra&lt;/a&gt;.  If you've ever written code to do numerical simulations which is rapidly in flux, you've probably used an unearthly combination of log files, subdirectories, and commit logs to keep track of which simulation was done with what parameters and what version of the code.  Sumatra wraps this all up in a very nice interface, and it takes very little modification to get it to work with an existing codebase.  I had already heard it mentioned on twitter, but the lightning talk showed how quick and easy to use it is, which definitely sold me on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sklearn-theano/sklearn-theano"&gt;Scikit-theano&lt;/a&gt;.  This is a nice package by Kyle Kastner to expose some complex estimators that are currently outside of the scope of the main scikit-learn project using a sklearn-like api, while using Theano under the hood for speed.  Anyone who is familiar with the sklearn API should be able to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="misc"/><category term="SciPy"/><category term="Python"/><category term="open source"/></entry><entry><title>Weapons of Math Destruction</title><link href="https://federicov.github.io/deception-by-mathematics.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2014-07-29T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2014-07-29T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Federico Vaggi</name></author><id>tag:federicov.github.io,2014-07-29:/deception-by-mathematics.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The miracle of the appropriateness of the language of mathematics for the formulation of the laws of physics is a wonderful gift which we neither understand nor deserve. We should be grateful for it and hope that it will remain valid in future research and that it will extend, for …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The miracle of the appropriateness of the language of mathematics for the formulation of the laws of physics is a wonderful gift which we neither understand nor deserve. We should be grateful for it and hope that it will remain valid in future research and that it will extend, for better or for worse, to our pleasure, even though perhaps also to our bafflement, to wide branches of learning.&lt;/em&gt; - Eugene Wigner, The Unreasonable Effectiveness of Mathematics in the Physical Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Trust and its role in the Scientific Enteprise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although radical skepticism is a consistent philosophy, it's not really a practical way to live our life.  We are all at the mercy of experts.  For example, when talking to a doctor who is discussing a complicated diagnosis with us, we assume that what she is telling us makes sense, even if we lack the expertise to critically evaluate her claims.  We don't extend the benefit of the doubt to everyone - if a PR person makes a claim about a product, most people will react skeptically and will want to verify it themselves.  Trust is an incredibly important resource, and once a group is seen as routinely exaggerating, it's very hard to gain back a positive reputation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to examine the role that trust plays in science.  Math has been incredibly important in physics for the past four centuries, and it's gradually gaining in importance in other domains.  Biology is one of the frontiers where math is expanding its influence, and it has led to the creation of entirely new disciplines such as bioinformatics, systems biology (my field), computational crystallography, biophysics, etc..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Biology and Math&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biologists are some of the most intelligent people that I know (and I'm not just saying that because my mother is one) but the typical biology curricula offers a smattering of statistics and very little advanced math.  This makes collaborations between mathematicians/physicists/computer scientists and biologists particularly challenging and, unlike families, every happy collaboration between theoreticians and experimentalists is different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that when starting a new collaboration, biologists often have to spend a long time explaining the subtleties of their particular problem to theoreticians, and theoreticians have to honestly discuss the relative pros and cons of different modeling approaches, and both parties have to agree on the correct level of abstraction.  There are some common misunderstandings.  Physicists think that everything can be modeled as an Ising model (if there's a problem, just add a little perturbation).  Biologists think that the fancier the math, the more sophisticated and clever is the approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fancy Looking Bullshit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expanding on that last point, biologists often lack the necessary mathematical basis to evalulate complex mathematical formalisms, and tend to assume that their collaborators are acting in good faith.  This is usually a good thing - but unfortunately it leaves the door open for unscrupulous people to peddle fancy looking bullshit.  I've been the lone theoretical person in a room of biologists listening to scientific talks where the speaker kept throwing around terms like 'non-linear', 'chaos', 'networks'  indiscriminately - and when asked simple questions at the end of the talk, clearly showed that they had no idea of what they were talking about.  I've seen meetings where theoreticians started scribbling down fancy looking formulas on the board for no purpose whatsoever except impressing their audience.  I've seen fancy-looking 3d graphs that added absolutely no information but gave an unwarranted air of complexity to an otherwise boring seminar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a particularly glaring example of this (in a different field) - read &lt;a href="http://retractionwatch.com/2013/09/19/fredrickson-losada-positivity-ratio-paper-partially-withdrawn/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; and weep.  The only reason this came to light, is that a fantastic graduate student, &lt;a href="http://steamtraen.blogspot.fr/"&gt;Nick Brown&lt;/a&gt;, with the help of &lt;a href="http://www.physics.nyu.edu/sokal/"&gt;Alan Sokal&lt;/a&gt; (another hero of mine) actually wasn't impressed by the fancy looking mathematics  and tried to get to the bottom of the story.  Of course, the person responsible for the mathematics in that paper is an executive consultant that describes himself this way:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Formerly, as Director of the Center for Advanced Research (CFAR) in Ann Arbor, Michigan, he conducted studies on the interaction dynamics and productivity of business teams that led him to implement a unique, scientifically based, approach to develop high performance teams. His pioneering work on applications of nonlinear dynamics to team interaction processes has been published in a number of prestigious scientific journals, and he has made several other contributions that have earned him worldwide recognition:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's someone that leveraged impressive looking mathematics to swindle not just scientists, but also human resource processionals, book editors, and multiple people that actually assumed that there must have been some substance behind the mathematics.  Every time something like this happens, it makes it much harder for honest and well meaning mathematicians to actually start a collaboration with an experimental collaborator.  Math has a very deep reservoir of good will, but it isn't infinite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As theoreticians, it is our duty to be honest about what we do, and the limits of our models.  This means being upfront and admitting when there is insufficient data to do anything productive, and being willing to call out bullshit for what it is - professional courtesy only goes so far, and deceiving well meaning people with buzzwords camouflaged as math poisons the well for all of us.  For people cooperating with theoreticians, beware people who throw out technical buzzwords for no apparent reason.  Unfortunately, bullshit is quite difficult to 'sniff out' if you lack sufficient background, and several bullshit artists are quite polished in their presentations - in that case, just ask someone you trust to look at their previous papers, or invite them into a meeting together and watch the sparks fly.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="misc"/><category term="[social psychology"/><category term="Sokal"/><category term="Nick Brown"/><category term="mathematics]"/></entry></feed>